[{"question":"The concept of the past as a foreign country is based on the idea that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"there used to be fewer foreigners in the United States than there are now.","index":"a"},{"value":"the boundaries of the country have changed over the past two hundred years.","index":"b"},{"value":"the population structure and characteristics have changed over time.","index":"c"},{"value":"immigrants have dramatically changed the demographics of the United States.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"During the twentieth century, life expectancy in the United States increased from about ____ to nearly 80.","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"40","index":"a"},{"value":"50","index":"b"},{"value":"60","index":"c"},{"value":"70","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"During the twentieth century, the average number of children born to women in the United States declined from____ to 2.1","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"5.0","index":"a"},{"value":"4.5","index":"b"},{"value":"4.0","index":"c"},{"value":"3.5","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"“Hatching, matching, and dispatching” is shorthand for the description of:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"population processes.","index":"a"},{"value":"population distribution.","index":"b"},{"value":"population characteristics.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Population structure is defined as:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"how many people there are in a given place.","index":"a"},{"value":"where people are located and why.","index":"b"},{"value":"how many males and females there are of each age.","index":"c"},{"value":"what people are like in a given place.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Globalization is rooted in demography most clearly as a result of:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"migration from developing to richer nations.","index":"a"},{"value":"low wage labor in rapidly growing developing nations.","index":"b"},{"value":"the spread of transportation and communication technology.","index":"c"},{"value":"the global increase in educational levels.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"One of the major demographic forces that is incendiary in the Middle East is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the high maternal mortality rate.","index":"a"},{"value":"high mortality from violent causes.","index":"b"},{"value":"refugees leaving the area.","index":"c"},{"value":"the impact of the youth bulge.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"The demographic roots of violence in Sub-Saharan Africa are related especially to:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the high maternal mortality rate.","index":"a"},{"value":"high mortality from violent causes.","index":"b"},{"value":"refugees leaving the area.","index":"c"},{"value":"the impact of the youth bulge.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"For the past few decades, the number of children born to Palestinian women has been about ____ times as many as have been born to Israeli women.","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"two","index":"a"},{"value":"three","index":"b"},{"value":"four","index":"c"},{"value":"five","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"The United States accepts more immigrants than any other country in the world, but the country with the highest number of immigrants per person is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Canada.","index":"a"},{"value":"Australia.","index":"b"},{"value":"the United Kingdom.","index":"c"},{"value":"France.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"With reference to Europe, the “demographic time bomb” usually refers to:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the rapid growth of the Muslim population.","index":"a"},{"value":"the impact of undocumented immigrants from sub-Saharan Africa.","index":"b"},{"value":"low fertility leading to the demise of the nuclear family.","index":"c"},{"value":"the rapid aging of the population.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Population growth alone would not have had such a huge impact on the environment were it not for the accompanying fact that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"people have been living longer.","index":"a"},{"value":"there has been an intensive increase in the use of resources.","index":"b"},{"value":"the atmospheric conditions have been shifting.","index":"c"},{"value":"humans have settled in increasingly vulnerable parts of the planet.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Geodemographics and spatial demography refer to the analysis of demographic data that does the following:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"takes business uses of demography into account.","index":"a"},{"value":"takes location of people being studied into account.","index":"b"},{"value":"takes globalization into account.","index":"c"},{"value":"takes Congressional apportionment into account.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Which of the following is a constitutionally mandated reason for conducting a census in the United States?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Drawing of congressional district boundaries","index":"a"},{"value":"Distribution of funds to counties based on population size","index":"b"},{"value":"Apportionment of seats in the US Senate","index":"c"},{"value":"Calculation of the percentage of the population that is eligible to vote","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"States that have a more liberal voting pattern are generally located _______ in the United States and are located ____ in Mexico:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"in the middle states; in the northern states","index":"a"},{"value":"on the coastal states; in the northern states","index":"b"},{"value":"on the coasts; in the southern states","index":"c"},{"value":"in the middle states; in the southern states","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Which of the following demographic phenomena is apt to have the LEAST impact on decisions that school districts have to make?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Patterns of in- and –out migration","index":"a"},{"value":"Changes in the age structure","index":"b"},{"value":"Trends in fertility","index":"c"},{"value":"Declines in the death rate","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Demographics are used in business marketing principally to accomplish the following:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Predict changes in the age structure","index":"a"},{"value":"Find the people who will buy a given product","index":"b"},{"value":"Avoid expensive litigation related to discrimination","index":"c"},{"value":"Reposition declining industries","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"The age group that is projected more quickly in the United States between 2010 and 2030 is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"10-19","index":"a"},{"value":"40-49","index":"b"},{"value":"65-74","index":"c"},{"value":"They are all projected to grow at the same rate.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"The PRIZM system used by Nielsen Claritas is a direct application of the concept of:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"site selection demographics.","index":"a"},{"value":"human resource demographics.","index":"b"},{"value":"geodemographics.","index":"c"},{"value":"investment demographics.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"Which of the following demographic characteristics would likely be of least importance in evaluating investments for their growth potential?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Rate of population growth","index":"a"},{"value":"Absolute size of the population","index":"b"},{"value":"Ethnic distribution of the population","index":"c"},{"value":"Age structure","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":1},{"question":"The term “demography” has Greek linguistic roots meaning “people” and “study of .“ ","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"At the beginning of the twentieth century, the number of Italian immigrants coming into the United States was similar to the number Mexican immigrants coming into the country at the beginning of the twenty-first century.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"The fact that demography is connected to nearly everything means that demography determines nearly everything.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"The presence of children in armies in sub-Saharan Africa is at least partly a side-effect of parents dying from HIV/AIDS.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"A youth bulge inevitably leads to conflict in human populations.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"An important factor in the growth of the Palestinian population has been the dramatic drop in the infant mortality rate.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"“Demographic fatigue” refers to the idea that as people get older they tend to tire more easily.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"Congressional redistricting in the United States is demographic in nature because geodemographic data are required to combat “gerrymandering.”","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"Cluster marketing is an application of the so-called “first law of geography.”","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"Life insurance companies and pension funds both make more money the longer that their customers live.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":1},{"question":"The world’s population at the time of the Agricultural (Neolithic) Revolution was approximately:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"4 million.","index":"a"},{"value":"40 million.","index":"b"},{"value":"400 million.","index":"c"},{"value":"4 billion.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Carrying capacity is lower for hunter-gatherers than for agriculturists because:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"their death rates are higher.","index":"a"},{"value":"they use the land extensively rather than intensively.","index":"b"},{"value":"they have fewer technological skills.","index":"c"},{"value":"birth rates regularly exceeded death rates.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Between the third and fifth centuries AD the world’s population declined somewhat, probably due to:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"the impact of Indonesian volcanic eruptions.","index":"a"},{"value":"higher mortality brought on by the early days of the Little Ice Age.","index":"b"},{"value":"collapse of the Roman Empire and famine and floods in China.","index":"c"},{"value":"the Irish Potato Famine.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Two hundred years ago, the world’s population was approximately:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"100 million.","index":"a"},{"value":"200 million.","index":"b"},{"value":"1 billion.","index":"c"},{"value":"2 billion.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Current projections suggest that we may reach a population of 9 billion in approximately:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"2025","index":"a"},{"value":"2050","index":"b"},{"value":"2075","index":"c"},{"value":"2100","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The total population of the world is currently increasing by about _____ million people per year:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"20","index":"a"},{"value":"40","index":"b"},{"value":"60","index":"c"},{"value":"80","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The Persian chess board story illustrates which of the following?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"The Queen as embodiment of female empowerment","index":"a"},{"value":"The power of doubling","index":"b"},{"value":"The dilemma of using logarithms","index":"c"},{"value":"A useful calculation of carrying capacity","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Population growth was slow for most of human history because:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"death rates were very high.","index":"a"},{"value":"abortion rates were very high.","index":"b"},{"value":"people preferred small families.","index":"c"},{"value":"low levels of technology always lead to low rates of growth.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The most important reason for the massive increase in the human population over the past two hundred years is:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the Green Revolution that increased agricultural productivity.","index":"a"},{"value":"the decline in the death rate.","index":"b"},{"value":"the increase in the birth rate.","index":"c"},{"value":"technology that has made it possible to live more places.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"If a country is thought to be on the verge of population implosion, it is probably located in:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"North America.","index":"a"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa.","index":"b"},{"value":"South Asia.","index":"c"},{"value":"Europe.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The total number of people who have ever lived is probably about:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"10 billion.","index":"a"},{"value":"30 billion.","index":"b"},{"value":"60 billion.","index":"c"},{"value":"90 billion.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"European expansion was characterized by east-west migration; since the end of World War II, world migration has been especially:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"a continuation of the east-west trend.","index":"a"},{"value":"a reversal of the east-west trend.","index":"b"},{"value":"a south-north trend.","index":"c"},{"value":"a north-south trend.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The five most populous countries in the world account for about ____ percent of the total world’s population.","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"10","index":"a"},{"value":"25","index":"b"},{"value":"50","index":"c"},{"value":"70","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The region of the world most negatively affected demographically by European expansion was:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Latin America.","index":"a"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa.","index":"b"},{"value":"Indian subcontinent.","index":"c"},{"value":"China.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"At about the time of the American Revolution, the United States had a birth that:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"was very similar to the birth rate in England at the time.","index":"a"},{"value":"was already lower than any currently developing nation.","index":"b"},{"value":"was higher than birth rates even in Sub-Saharan Africa at that time.","index":"c"},{"value":"was comparable to the highest national birth rates in the world today.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Mortality and fertility trends in Canada are currently most like which of the following countries/regions of the world?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"United States","index":"a"},{"value":"Western Europe","index":"b"},{"value":"Latin America","index":"c"},{"value":"Japan","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"Population growth in Mexico was very rapid until recently because of a substantial delay in:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"its fertility decline.","index":"a"},{"value":"its mortality decline.","index":"b"},{"value":"migration out of the country to the U.S.","index":"c"},{"value":"improving agricultural productivity.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"An important demographic consequence of very low fertility in Europe is that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"European countries have been actively recruiting immigrants to fill in the younger ages.","index":"a"},{"value":"European countries are aging.","index":"b"},{"value":"the status of women has risen dramatically.","index":"c"},{"value":"taxes have risen sharply in order to pay benefits to the elderly.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The most distinguishing demographic feature of the North Africa/Western Asia region of the world is its:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"youth bulge.","index":"a"},{"value":"rapidly aging population.","index":"b"},{"value":"High rate of out-migration.","index":"c"},{"value":"Intransigently high level of infant mortality.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"The two most populous nations of sub-Saharan Africa are:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Nigeria and Congo","index":"a"},{"value":"Ghana and Zimbabwe.","index":"b"},{"value":"Congo (Kinshasa) and Ethiopia.","index":"c"},{"value":"Nigeria and Ethiopia.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":2},{"question":"China’s Great Leap Forward in 1958 helped to bring down that country’s high death rate.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"A baby is born somewhere in the world every four seconds.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"The United Nations projects that the population of the world will double again over the next 40 years.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"The majority of people ever born are alive at this moment.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"Nearly four in ten humans live in either China or the Indian subcontinent.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"Migration has been the single most important cause of population growth over time in the United States.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"The drop in fertility in China is largely a result of its one-child policy.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"Fertility is so low in Japan that it seems to have its own “one-child policy.”","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"India’s demography is so diverse that some of its southern states actually have fertility levels that are below replacement.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"Bangladesh (originally known as East Pakistan) has birth and death rates that are more like those in India than in Pakistan (which was originally known as West Pakistan).","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":2},{"question":"An early population doctrine that advocated the idea that quality was better than quantity when it came to the number of humans is attributable to:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Confucius.","index":"a"},{"value":"Plato.","index":"b"},{"value":"Cicero.","index":"c"},{"value":"Ibn Khaldun.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The early idea that population growth is inherently good because it leads to specialization and higher incomes is attributed to:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Confucius.","index":"a"},{"value":"Plato.","index":"b"},{"value":"Cicero.","index":"c"},{"value":"Ibn Khaldun.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The cultural reawakening of Europe after the Middle Ages is attributable especially to which of the following?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Contact with the Mediterranean Islamic world","index":"a"},{"value":"The receding of the plague","index":"b"},{"value":"Growth of cities","index":"c"},{"value":"The Columbian Exchange","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The person often called the “father of demography” is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Thomas Robert Malthus.","index":"a"},{"value":"Achille Guillard.","index":"b"},{"value":"John Graunt.","index":"c"},{"value":"Willam Petty.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Which of the following events/periods did NOT precede the publication of Malthus’s book on population?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"French Revolution","index":"a"},{"value":"Columbian Exchange","index":"b"},{"value":"Enlightenment","index":"c"},{"value":"Industrial Revolution","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Which of the following people was LEAST likely to champion the rights of women?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Malthus","index":"a"},{"value":"Condorcet","index":"b"},{"value":"J.S. Mill","index":"c"},{"value":"Marx","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Which of the following thinkers would be MOST likely to agree with Marx that problems of the poor were due less to population than to inequities in the social system?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Godwin","index":"a"},{"value":"J.S. Mill","index":"b"},{"value":"Dumont","index":"c"},{"value":"Durkheim","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The essential element of Malthus’s Principle of Population was that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"moral restraint was critical to the survival of the human population.","index":"a"},{"value":"positive checks tended to counter-balance preventive checks.","index":"b"},{"value":"population grew geometrically while food increased arithmetically.","index":"c"},{"value":"the passion between the sexes must be constrained by social institutions.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Malthus’s concept of positive checks to population growth would conform most closely to what we call:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"drought and famine.","index":"a"},{"value":"methods of contraception.","index":"b"},{"value":"moral restraint.","index":"c"},{"value":"causes of mortality.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Which of the following is LEAST consistent with Malthus’s idea about moral restraint?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Postpone marriage","index":"a"},{"value":"Practice safe sex prior to marriage","index":"b"},{"value":"Marry only when you can afford children","index":"c"},{"value":"Avoid birth control after marriage","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The important political implication of Malthus’s theory regarding population was that:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"the poor were to blame for their own poverty.","index":"a"},{"value":"poverty is the product of unjust social institutions.","index":"b"},{"value":"the niggardliness of nature produces human unhappiness.","index":"c"},{"value":"it is important to teach methods of birth control to the poor.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The influential theorist who described his own theory as ‘the doctrine of Malthus applied with manifold force to the whole animal and vegetable kingdoms” was:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Karl Marx.","index":"a"},{"value":"J.S. Mill.","index":"b"},{"value":"Charles Darwin.","index":"c"},{"value":"Émile Durkheim.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The important political implication of the Marxian theory regarding population was that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the poor were to blame for their own poverty.","index":"a"},{"value":"poverty is the product of unjust social institutions.","index":"b"},{"value":"the niggardliness of nature produces human unhappiness.","index":"c"},{"value":"it is important to teach methods of birth control to the poor.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The Chinese government’s approach to dealing with population growth over the past several decades could be characterized as a mix of the ideas of Marx and:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"J.S. Mill.","index":"a"},{"value":"Ibn Khaldun.","index":"b"},{"value":"Condorcet.","index":"c"},{"value":"Malthus.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"An important element that J.S. Mill added to population thinking was:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"a sudden increase in income would promote thrift and provide a motivation to limit fertility.","index":"a"},{"value":"social aspiration is the root cause of a desire to limit fertility.","index":"b"},{"value":"population growth leads to greater societal specialization.","index":"c"},{"value":"populations over time have transitioned from high birth and death rates to low birth and death rates.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"An important element that Durkheim added to population thinking was:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"fear of slipping socially was a motivation to limit fertility.","index":"a"},{"value":"social aspiration is the root cause of a desire to limit fertility.","index":"b"},{"value":"population growth leads to greater societal specialization.","index":"c"},{"value":"a sudden increase in income would promote thrift and provide a motivation to limit fertility.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The reformulation of the demographic transition theory was inspired especially by:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Neo-Marxian views that emerged after the collapse of the Soviet Union.","index":"a"},{"value":"new ideas brought forward by the theory of demographic change and response.","index":"b"},{"value":"ideas emerging from the European Fertility Project at Princeton.","index":"c"},{"value":"ideas emerging from Samuel Huntington’s work on “Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order.”","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The theory of demographic change and response added which of the following to the demographic transition?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"The concept of rational choice as a key element in understanding human behavior","index":"a"},{"value":"The concepts of secularization and modernization","index":"b"},{"value":"The concept of wealth flow","index":"c"},{"value":"The concept of linking demography to the lives of individuals and families","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The Easterlin relative cohort size hypothesis draws its underlying concepts from the earlier writings of:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Malthus.","index":"a"},{"value":"Condorcet.","index":"b"},{"value":"Mill.","index":"c"},{"value":"Dumont.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"The so-called “second demographic transition” would be most closely associated with which of the following transitions associated with the overall demographic transition?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Fertility transition","index":"a"},{"value":"Age transition","index":"b"},{"value":"Urban transition","index":"c"},{"value":"Family and household transition","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":3},{"question":"Doctrines are usually based on fact, whereas theories are speculative in nature.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"The doctrine of mercantilism maintained that the more people a nation had, the more it could produce, and thus the wealthier it would be.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"It is likely that if the French Revolution had not occurred, Malthus’s book on Population would never have been published.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"Neo-Malthusians are the people who influenced Darwin’s ideas about evolution.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"Malthus and Marx agreed on the causes of population growth, but not on the consequences.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"Marx’s denial of the potential for population problems in a socialist society were proven correct by what later happened in Russia and China.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"The original version of the demographic transition theory was closely tied to the concept of modernization.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"Two key concepts added during the reformulation of the demographic transition theory were secularization and diffusion.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"The important aspect of the theory of demographic change and response is that it emphasizes the role of individual initiative in responding to demographic change.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"A key element in the Easterlin hypothesis is that the relative size of cohorts can influence the way in which people and societies change over time.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":3},{"question":"The word ‘census’ comes from the Latin meaning:","answer":"","option":[{"value":"per 100.","index":"a"},{"value":"political status.","index":"b"},{"value":"taxing (110).","index":"c"},{"value":"subjects.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Which of the following purposes for taking a census was NOT very important to the Romans?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Military obligations","index":"a"},{"value":"Determination of political status","index":"b"},{"value":"Measurement of population growth rate","index":"c"},{"value":"Taxation","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The word ‘statistic’ is derived from the German word meaning:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"applied mathematics.","index":"a"},{"value":"facts about a state.","index":"b"},{"value":"census or survey.","index":"c"},{"value":"boring stuff.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Censuses designed specifically to inquire about population characteristics became most popular in which century?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"14th","index":"a"},{"value":"17th","index":"b"},{"value":"19th","index":"c"},{"value":"20th","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Nigeria’s modern censuses have been contentious mainly because of:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"corruption associated with oil revenue.","index":"a"},{"value":"a history of civil wars.","index":"b"},{"value":"ethnic tensions and rivalries.","index":"c"},{"value":"north-south differences in educational attainment.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Lebanon has not had a census since 1932 mainly because of tension between:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Arab and French speakers.","index":"a"},{"value":"Christians and Muslims.","index":"b"},{"value":"higher and lower status persons.","index":"c"},{"value":"Lebanese and Israelis.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The single most important purpose of the census in the United States is to:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"apportion seats in the House of Representatives.","index":"a"},{"value":"provide marketers with accurate data about potential customers.","index":"b"},{"value":"apportion seats in the U.S. Senate.","index":"c"},{"value":"provide policy planners with accurate demographic information.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"In the 2010 Census of the United States, the “long form” data was replaced by information from:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the Demographic and Health Survey.","index":"a"},{"value":"the Current Population Survey.","index":"b"},{"value":"the Accuracy and Coverage Evaluation Survey.","index":"c"},{"value":"the American Community Survey.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"If you want to find data on education of Americans at the census tract level for 2010, the best source will be:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the short form on the 2010 Census.","index":"a"},{"value":"the American Community Survey.","index":"b"},{"value":"the Current Population Survey.","index":"c"},{"value":"the US Department of Education.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The United States, Mexico, and Canada all include people in the census on the following basis:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"De facto residence","index":"a"},{"value":"Usual residence","index":"b"},{"value":"De jure residence","index":"c"},{"value":"Common law residence","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The existence of a differential undercount by race in the United States was first discovered after which census?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"1890","index":"a"},{"value":"1920","index":"b"},{"value":"1940","index":"c"},{"value":"1950","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a method employed to measure coverage error in the census?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Demographic balancing equation","index":"a"},{"value":"Demographic analysis","index":"b"},{"value":"Dual-system estimation","index":"c"},{"value":"Differential undercount","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT typically considered to be a “vital event”?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Birth","index":"a"},{"value":"Death","index":"b"},{"value":"Migration","index":"c"},{"value":"Marriage","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"For those countries that do not conduct a census, which of the following is the best possible substitute for a census?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Demographic and Health Survey","index":"a"},{"value":"Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey","index":"b"},{"value":"Current Population Survey","index":"c"},{"value":"Population Register","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The United States, Canada, and Mexico all collect national demographic data on a monthly survey basis, focusing largely on:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"labor force participation.","index":"a"},{"value":"migration.","index":"b"},{"value":"consumer expenditures.","index":"c"},{"value":"income and program participation.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"If you wanted to obtain recent detailed population data about a sub-Saharan African country, the most likely source of such information would be the:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"INDEPTH Network surveillance sites.","index":"a"},{"value":"Demographic and Health Survey.","index":"b"},{"value":"World Fertility Survey.","index":"c"},{"value":"Family and Fertility Survey.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"If you were interested in doing historical demographic research in China, which of the following sources of data would most likely be available to you?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Family genealogies","index":"a"},{"value":"Population registers","index":"b"},{"value":"Church parish records","index":"c"},{"value":"School enrollment data","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"In order to understand the spatial nature of demographic phenomena, a researcher needs to have:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"individual-level census data.","index":"a"},{"value":"detailed survey data.","index":"b"},{"value":"administrative data such as utility records.","index":"c"},{"value":"geo-referenced demographic data.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Geodemographics requires at least the following two elements:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"geo-referenced demographic data and remotely sensed data.","index":"a"},{"value":"GIS software and spatial statistical tools.","index":"b"},{"value":"demographic concepts and spatial statistical tools.","index":"c"},{"value":"GIS software and geo-referenced demographic data.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"Which of the following inventions is NOT closely related to the census?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Cell phone","index":"a"},{"value":"Photo-optical scanning devices","index":"b"},{"value":"Computer","index":"c"},{"value":"Card punch tabulating machine","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":4},{"question":"The Domesday Book in England represents the first modern census.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The period of time during which modern censuses emerged is also the period of European expansion.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"Germany has always had a population register rather than conducting a census.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The US, Canadian and Mexican censuses all ask questions about race and ethnicity.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"A major issue with respect to sampling in the census has to do with its use to estimate the differential undercount.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The principal benefit of the American Community Survey is that it is less expensive than a census.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The first census of Canada was taken in 1666.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The first census in Mexico was taken in 1980.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"Public Use Microdata are individual-level data from past censuses in the US and other countries.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The US Census Bureau has played a significant role in the development of computer technology.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":4},{"question":"The health and mortality transition does NOT typically involve which of the following?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Shift in deaths from the younger to the older ages","index":"a"},{"value":"Greater control over the natural environment","index":"b"},{"value":"Shift in causes of death from communicable to degenerative","index":"c"},{"value":"Permanently greater spread in the ages at which people die","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"For most of human history, up to the modern era, life expectancy was probably about:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"20-30 years.","index":"a"},{"value":"30-40 years.","index":"b"},{"value":"40-50 years.","index":"c"},{"value":"50-60 years.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Life expectancy during the Roman era was probably little more than ___ years:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"20","index":"a"},{"value":"30","index":"b"},{"value":"40","index":"c"},{"value":"50","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"When life expectancy is 30, about ___ percent of children die before their fifth birthday, compared to ___ percent when life expectancy is 80:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"40; 1","index":"a"},{"value":"50; 1","index":"b"},{"value":"50; 10","index":"c"},{"value":"60; 10","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Which of the following was LEAST likely to have influenced the decline in mortality in the United States prior to World War II?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Improved diet","index":"a"},{"value":"Better hygiene","index":"b"},{"value":"Availability of penicillin","index":"c"},{"value":"Availability of smallpox vaccinations","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"World War II was a turning point in world mortality decline because:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"it taught the world the value of human life.","index":"a"},{"value":"it created new ways of coping with violent death.","index":"b"},{"value":"it led to the development of the germ theory.","index":"c"},{"value":"it led to the spread of death control technology around the world.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The basic lesson of the nutrition transition concept is that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"you are what you eat.","index":"a"},{"value":"Americanization is bad for your health.","index":"b"},{"value":"diets must adapt to circumstances.","index":"c"},{"value":"being fat is healthier now than it used to be.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The planned obsolescence theory of human aging suggests that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"we undergo a process of senescence as we age.","index":"a"},{"value":"our bodies are like machines that wear out.","index":"b"},{"value":"our cells have a built-in time clock that eventually stops.","index":"c"},{"value":"there is a high probability of Alzheimer’s if we live long enough.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The oldest verified age to which a human has ever lived is just over:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"100 years.","index":"a"},{"value":"110 years.","index":"b"},{"value":"120 years.","index":"c"},{"value":"130 years.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Which of the following is most true when it comes to longevity?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"It is measured by the concept of life span.","index":"a"},{"value":"About 35 percent of the variability is due to inherited characteristics.","index":"b"},{"value":"About 50 percent of the variability is due to economic factors.","index":"c"},{"value":"The single most important element in variability is your outlook on life.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The age at which the average human has the highest risk of death is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"0","index":"a"},{"value":"1","index":"b"},{"value":"5","index":"c"},{"value":"15","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"the age at which the average human has the lowest risk of death is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"0","index":"a"},{"value":"1","index":"b"},{"value":"5","index":"c"},{"value":"15","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"If everyone survived to age 100 and then died shortly after that, the process would be called:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"rectangularization of mortality.","index":"a"},{"value":"suppression of death rates.","index":"b"},{"value":"gender inequality in mortality.","index":"c"},{"value":"a miracle.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"In which of the following regions of the world would you be most likely to still find countries where men live longer than women?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"The Middle East","index":"a"},{"value":"South Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"Central America","index":"c"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Throughout most of human history, the major causes of death have been related to:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"infectious diseases.","index":"a"},{"value":"pregnancy-related diseases.","index":"b"},{"value":"smoking.","index":"c"},{"value":"injuries.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"In a low mortality society such as the United States, the principal causes of death are related to:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"infectious diseases.","index":"a"},{"value":"pregnancy-related diseases.","index":"b"},{"value":"noncommunicable conditions.","index":"c"},{"value":"injuries.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The most important “real” causes of death in the United States are related to:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"tobacco use.","index":"a"},{"value":"drug and alcohol misuse.","index":"b"},{"value":"diet and activity patterns.","index":"c"},{"value":"microbial agents.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Which of the following statistical concepts is NOT directly used to calculate life expectancy?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Age-adjusted death rate","index":"a"},{"value":"Age-specific death rate","index":"b"},{"value":"Probability of dying between two different ages","index":"c"},{"value":"Number of years lived","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"Which of the following characteristics is least predictive of low levels of mortality?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Higher social status rather than lower","index":"a"},{"value":"Urban residence rather than rural","index":"b"},{"value":"Higher levels of education rather than lower","index":"c"},{"value":"Being married rather than divorced","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The “Hispanic Paradox” refers to the phenomenon of:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"undocumented immigrants entering the United States with untreated tuberculosis.","index":"a"},{"value":"Americanization being bad for your health.","index":"b"},{"value":"high levels of obesity among Hispanics in the United States.","index":"c"},{"value":"lower death rates for Hispanics than non-Hispanics in the United States.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":5},{"question":"The plague was hitting Spain at about the same time that Spaniards were spreading disease to the Americas.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"The plague disappeared from Europe at about the time that the Industrial Revolution was getting started.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"Medical advances were the main reason for the decline of mortality in Europe and the United States in the 19th and early 20th centuries.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"Life expectancy in Russia is now significantly higher than it was thirty years ago.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"The available evidence suggests that if we could get rid of Alzheimer’s disease, humans could live nearly forever.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"Life expectancy and lifespan both refer to the highest age to which humans can expect to live.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"The finding that your initials might affect your life expectancy provide evidence of possible psychological influences on mortality.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"Given the current world averages, an infant mortality rate of 100 would be considered low.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"In human populations, there is a universal survival advantage of women.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"The crude death rate is called “crude” because it does not take into account the age and sex distribution of the population.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":5},{"question":"The fertility transition does NOT necessarily involve which of the following?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"A shift to a higher probability that children born will survive to adulthood","index":"a"},{"value":"A shift from low to high control over reproduction","index":"b"},{"value":"A shift from family building by fate to family building by design","index":"c"},{"value":"Parental freedom from the bondage of unwanted children","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"“Natural” fertility in most populations produces an average of about how many children?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"2-3","index":"a"},{"value":"4-5","index":"b"},{"value":"6-7","index":"c"},{"value":"8-9","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The world’s most prolific woman had 69 children, but the probable highest average number of children per woman for a whole society is about:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"7","index":"a"},{"value":"16","index":"b"},{"value":"23","index":"c"},{"value":"35","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Hutterite society has been notable especially for having high fertility in the context of:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"low mortality.","index":"a"},{"value":"dense urban life.","index":"b"},{"value":"acceptance of abortion.","index":"c"},{"value":"late age at marriage.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a likely explanation for the high fertility that existed for most of human history?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Need to overcome high mortality","index":"a"},{"value":"Children are a source of security and labor for their parents","index":"b"},{"value":"The desire for sons","index":"c"},{"value":"Religious objections to the use of contraception","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The concept of accepting calculated choice as being a valid element in marital fertility decisions is one of the:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"differences between fecundity and fertility.","index":"a"},{"value":"preconditions for a substantial fertility decline.","index":"b"},{"value":"proximate determinants of fertility.","index":"c"},{"value":"diffusion processes leading to a drop in fertility.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which of the following is LEAST likely to represent a long term explanation for a decline in fertility?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Population pressure created by low mortality","index":"a"},{"value":"Increasing empowerment of women","index":"b"},{"value":"Improving levels of education","index":"c"},{"value":"Spread of westernization","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The idea that couples strive to maintain a balance between how many surviving children they have and how many they want is associated with:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"the preconditions for a substantial fertility decline.","index":"a"},{"value":"the exogenous factors that influence reproductive behavior.","index":"b"},{"value":"the new household economics of fertility behavior.","index":"c"},{"value":"the demographic linkage between fertility and reproductive health.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The economic theory of children suggests that in deciding how many children to have, parents are doing the following:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Trading off between quality and quantity","index":"a"},{"value":"Balancing supply and demand","index":"b"},{"value":"Finding a mini-max solution to the marginal costs of children","index":"c"},{"value":"Looking for the diminishing returns to opportunity costs","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which of the following characteristics of women is most closely associated with fertility levels?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Educational level","index":"a"},{"value":"Labor force participation","index":"b"},{"value":"Religious preference","index":"c"},{"value":"Wealth","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which of the following is the LEAST important proximate determinant of fertility in terms of its average effect on fertility levels?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Abortion","index":"a"},{"value":"Age at entry into sexual unions","index":"b"},{"value":"Voluntary abstinence","index":"c"},{"value":"Breast-feeding","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Among women in their late 30s and early 40s in the United States, the most popular form of contraception is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"the condom.","index":"a"},{"value":"the pill.","index":"b"},{"value":"sterilization.","index":"c"},{"value":"the IUD.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The available evidence suggests that the most widely used method of birth control in the world is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the pill.","index":"a"},{"value":"the condom.","index":"b"},{"value":"voluntary abstinence.","index":"c"},{"value":"abortion.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The total fertility rate measures:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the total number of children born in a population.","index":"a"},{"value":"the total number of surviving children that a woman will have in her lifetime.","index":"b"},{"value":"the total number of children ever born to a woman at the end of her reproductive career.","index":"c"},{"value":"the total number of projected children ever born per woman if ASFRs do not change.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The net reproduction rate is also known as the:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"total fertility rate.","index":"a"},{"value":"fertility index.","index":"b"},{"value":"generational replacement rate.","index":"c"},{"value":"mean length of generation.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Data on fertility intentions help to sort out the difference between:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"timing and quantum of births.","index":"a"},{"value":"gross and net reproduction.","index":"b"},{"value":"general and age-specific rates.","index":"c"},{"value":"proximate and distal determinants of fertility.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which region of the world currently has the highest levels of fertility?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Africa","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"Latin America and the Caribbean","index":"c"},{"value":"Oceania","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The evidence suggests that an important impediment to higher fertility levels in Europe is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"lack of gender equity within marriage.","index":"a"},{"value":"the widespread use of abortion.","index":"b"},{"value":"a continually sluggish economic environment.","index":"c"},{"value":"the “glass ceiling” for women in the workplace.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The impact of China’s One-Child Policy on that country’s fertility level can best be described as:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"having provided the initial impetus for a fertility decline.","index":"a"},{"value":"allowing China to mirror similar fertility declines among its neighbors.","index":"b"},{"value":"facilitating an already existing decline in fertility.","index":"c"},{"value":"important only because it accompanied measures of social equity.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which statement is LEAST descriptive of current fertility trends in the United States?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"An increasing fraction of babies born are Hispanic.","index":"a"},{"value":"High levels of cohabitation are depressing the birth rate.","index":"b"},{"value":"Teenage birth rates are declining.","index":"c"},{"value":"The average age at motherhood is increasing.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":6},{"question":"The healthier a woman is, the later is the age at which she experiences menarche.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The opportunity costs of children change over time as social circumstances change.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The diffusion of ideas such as desired family size is enhanced by the existence of rigidly defined social strata.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The later a woman marries, the more children she is likely to have.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"Withdrawal is one of the more effective methods of fertility control for women who don’t use the pill.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"Abortion rates tend to be highest when other methods of contraception are not readily available to women.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The crude birth rate is called “crude” because it does not take into account the age and sex of people at risk of having a baby.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The most dramatic decline in fertility in the recent past has been in East Asia.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"The United Kingdom is one of the few European countries in which fertility has recently risen above replacement level.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"Margaret Sanger’s work revealed that contraception was known and practiced by western European women, but not by southern European women.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":6},{"question":"Which of the following changes is required if you are to be migrant, not just a mover?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Change in commute pattern","index":"a"},{"value":"Change of job","index":"b"},{"value":"New spouse or significant other","index":"c"},{"value":"Movement of total round of daily activities","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The most common definition of a permanent migrant is someone who has lived in the new location for at least ___.","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"1 year (264).","index":"a"},{"value":"5 years","index":"b"},{"value":"10 years","index":"c"},{"value":"there is no such definition","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The difference between an immigrant and in-migrant is that:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"an in-migrant is always a legal migrant whereas an immigrant is not.","index":"a"},{"value":"an immigrant is usually a male whereas an in-migrant is not.","index":"b"},{"value":"an in-migrant is someone whose place of origin in known whereas an immigrant’s origin is unknown.","index":"c"},{"value":"an immigrant is usually an international migrant whereas an in-migrant may be either an internal or an international migrant.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"If we knew that 13 percent of the U.S. population in 2010 was foreign-born, we would have information about:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the flow of immigrants.","index":"a"},{"value":"the stock of immigrants.","index":"b"},{"value":"the influx of immigrants.","index":"c"},{"value":"the characteristics of immigrants.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The U.S. Census Bureau defines a migrant as someone who has moved at least to another:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"city","index":"a"},{"value":"county","index":"b"},{"value":"state","index":"c"},{"value":"country","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"Which of the following formulas measures net migration?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"IM/P","index":"a"},{"value":"IM + OM","index":"b"},{"value":"IM – OM","index":"c"},{"value":"OM/P","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The migration rate that uses the demographic balancing equation in its calculation is based on the:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"migration effectiveness method.","index":"a"},{"value":"components of change method.","index":"b"},{"value":"forward survival method.","index":"c"},{"value":"gross migration rate method.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"In his classic study of the push-pull theory of migration, Ravenstein argued that the most important motivation to move is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"the desire to get ahead.","index":"a"},{"value":"the need to escape an unpleasant situation.","index":"b"},{"value":"the desire of avoid poverty.","index":"c"},{"value":"the need to stay close to family members.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The concept of intervening obstacles reflects the fact that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"career advancement can alter migration plans.","index":"a"},{"value":"the choice to migrate may not actually lead to migration.","index":"b"},{"value":"the probability is low that any given person will migrate.","index":"c"},{"value":"people are likely to move to closer places than to far places.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT one of De Jong and Fawcett’s major concepts in the migration decision-making process?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Propensity toward migration","index":"a"},{"value":"Motivation to migrate","index":"b"},{"value":"Decision to become a migrant","index":"c"},{"value":"Consequences of migration","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"Migrants tend disproportionately to be:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"older people.","index":"a"},{"value":"women.","index":"b"},{"value":"young adults (275).","index":"c"},{"value":"minority group members.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The dominant current pattern of migration within the United States is out of the ___ and into the ___:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Northeast; south","index":"a"},{"value":"South; west","index":"b"},{"value":"West; south","index":"c"},{"value":"Midwest; west","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"If we knew that a migrant had gone to a particular place to join relatives there, we would probably be talking about the process of:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"return migration.","index":"a"},{"value":"chain migration.","index":"b"},{"value":"international migration.","index":"c"},{"value":"step migration.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The new household economic theory of migration suggests that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"household decision-making is more important than individual decision-making.","index":"a"},{"value":"neo-classical approaches to migration are fatally flawed.","index":"b"},{"value":"migration is a way to diversify a family’s sources of income.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The world systems theory of migration suggests that:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"once migration has begun, it will take on a life of its own.","index":"a"},{"value":"migration will perpetuated by international organizations.","index":"b"},{"value":"peripheral countries send migrants to core countries.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The analysis of Massey and his associates suggests that which of the following is the single best explanation of international migration?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"New household economics of migration","index":"a"},{"value":"World systems theory of migration","index":"b"},{"value":"Cumulative causation perspective on migration","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"A person entering the United States without documents is committing which type of crime?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Misdemeanor","index":"a"},{"value":"Serious","index":"b"},{"value":"Felony","index":"c"},{"value":"This is not a crime","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The country that currently sends the greatest number of migrants to other countries is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"China.","index":"a"},{"value":"India.","index":"b"},{"value":"Mexico.","index":"c"},{"value":"Philippines.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"During which period of time has the United States had the highest percentage of the population that was foreign-born?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"1820-1829","index":"a"},{"value":"1900-1909","index":"b"},{"value":"1940-1949","index":"c"},{"value":"2000-present","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"Which of the following is typically NOT a consequence of migration for the donor area?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Receipt of remittances","index":"a"},{"value":"Loss of young people","index":"b"},{"value":"Increase in number of older people","index":"c"},{"value":"Weakening of kinship relations","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":7},{"question":"The available evidence suggests that human beings are by nature mobile creatures, which explains the migration transition.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"A sojourner is considered to be residentially mobile, but not a migrant.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"Migration is the simplest of the three demographic processes to measure.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"In the United States, males are more likely to migrate than are females.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"The Great Migration refers to the movement of both whites and blacks out of the south into the northern states.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"Modern migration from Mexico to the United States began with a guest worker program.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"Guest worker programs are generally successful because it means that governments can readily send migrants back to their home country.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"The pattern of east to west migration has existed in both the United States and Europe.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"The majority of recent immigrants to Canada are from Europe.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"Unlike in the United States, slavery was never legal in either Canada or Mexico.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":7},{"question":"Which of the following is not necessarily characteristic of the age transition?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"A shift from a very young population to an older population","index":"a"},{"value":"A so-called demographic dividend","index":"b"},{"value":"A shift from a male majority to a female majority","index":"c"},{"value":"A middle stage with a large young adult population","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The idea that different behavior is expected of people according to their age is an example of:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"age discrimination.","index":"a"},{"value":"cohort influences on the age structure.","index":"b"},{"value":"Marxian thought.","index":"c"},{"value":"age stratification.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Cohort flow captures the idea that:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"historical events similarly affect people of the same age.","index":"a"},{"value":"people born at the same time tend to die at the same time.","index":"b"},{"value":"cohort effects are more important than either period or age effects.","index":"c"},{"value":"the composition of a population is determined by its pattern of birth cohorts.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"If we are comparing the rate of pregnancy-related deaths among young adult women now with rates from 50 years ago, we are most likely trying to understand the:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"age effect.","index":"a"},{"value":"period effect.","index":"b"},{"value":"cohort effect.","index":"c"},{"value":"All of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The high sex ratio at birth in China is probably a side-effect of:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"the widespread use of abortion as a method of birth control.","index":"a"},{"value":"the popularity of the IUD as a contraceptive.","index":"b"},{"value":"the pressure in Chinese society to have daughters.","index":"c"},{"value":"the one-child policy.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"A young age structure tends to have ____; whereas an older age structure tends to have ______.","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"More females than males; more males than females","index":"a"},{"value":"More males than females; more females than males","index":"b"},{"value":"More females than males; more females than males","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Which of the following countries has the youngest age structure?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Italy","index":"a"},{"value":"Mexico","index":"b"},{"value":"Nigeria","index":"c"},{"value":"United States","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The early impact of mortality decline on the age structure is to:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"make it younger.","index":"a"},{"value":"make it older.","index":"b"},{"value":"make it bulge in the middle.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The long-term impact of a fertility decline on the age structure is to:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"make it younger.","index":"a"},{"value":"make it older.","index":"b"},{"value":"make it bulge in the middle.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"If you see an age pyramid that caves in at the younger ages, the most likely explanation is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"declining fertility.","index":"a"},{"value":"increasing mortality.","index":"b"},{"value":"declining mortality.","index":"c"},{"value":"out-migration.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The short-term impact of an increase in migration on the age structure is to:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"make it younger.","index":"a"},{"value":"make it older.","index":"b"},{"value":"make it bulge in the middle.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The so-called ‘age dividend’ or ‘demographic windfall’ is associated with which of the following types of age structures?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Bulge in the working age population","index":"a"},{"value":"Youth bulge","index":"b"},{"value":"Age rectangularization","index":"c"},{"value":"Hourglass economy age pattern","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Which demographic process is most responsible for the age dividend/demographic dividend/demographic windfall?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Rapid drop in infant mortality","index":"a"},{"value":"Rapid rise in life expectancy","index":"b"},{"value":"Rapid drop in fertility","index":"c"},{"value":"Rapid rate of immigration","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The common designation of age 65 as the beginning of old age is based largely on:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"the average age of retirement in the United States.","index":"a"},{"value":"the individual aging process that lowers productivity after age 65.","index":"b"},{"value":"historical custom.","index":"c"},{"value":"the proportion of people alive past that age.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The single most important influence on the percent of the population that is older is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"the fertility rate.","index":"a"},{"value":"the mortality rate.","index":"b"},{"value":"the migration rate.","index":"c"},{"value":"None of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The country with the greatest number of people aged 65 and older is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"China.","index":"a"},{"value":"Italy.","index":"b"},{"value":"Japan.","index":"c"},{"value":"United States.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"The country with the highest percentage of people aged 65 and older is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"China.","index":"a"},{"value":"Italy.","index":"b"},{"value":"Japan.","index":"c"},{"value":"United States.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Disability-free life expectancy is essentially that age at which we transition from:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"work to retirement.","index":"a"},{"value":"marriage to widowhood.","index":"b"},{"value":"sickness to health.","index":"c"},{"value":"The Third Age to the Fourth Age.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Which of the following is the most detailed method of projecting a population?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Cohort component method","index":"a"},{"value":"Components of growth method","index":"b"},{"value":"Extrapolation method","index":"c"},{"value":"Demographic analysis method","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"Population momentum is most influenced by the proportion of the population that is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"under 15.","index":"a"},{"value":"older than 65.","index":"b"},{"value":"women in the reproductive years.","index":"c"},{"value":"foreign-born.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":8},{"question":"A society that has a high proportion of middle-aged people is likely to be economically wealthier than a society that has a high proportion of children.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"In most human societies, more females are born than males.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"In most human societies, there are more women at the older ages than there are men.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"The impact of mortality decline is more to increase the size of the population than to change the age structure.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"The dependency ratio measures the ratio of the population of working age to the population of dependent age.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"The impact of fertility decline is more to decrease the size of the population than to change the age structure.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"Mexico is currently in the midst of its own “age dividend” or “demographic windfall.”","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"If all people aged 65 and older lived in the same country, it would be the third most populous country in the world.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"The majority of older people live in the more developed countries.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"A population projection and a population forecast refer to the same concept.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":8},{"question":"The urban transition can occur only if which of the following is taking place?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Societal modernization","index":"a"},{"value":"Decline in agricultural activity","index":"b"},{"value":"City population is growing faster than rural population","index":"c"},{"value":"Industrialization is occurring in both rural and urban areas","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT one of the ways in which urban places are normally defined?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Population size","index":"a"},{"value":"Population density","index":"b"},{"value":"Extent of agricultural activities","index":"c"},{"value":"Extent of manufacturing activities","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"At the beginning of the nineteenth century, England was already one of the world’s most urban countries with about what percent of the population living in places of 30,000 people or more?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"10","index":"a"},{"value":"20","index":"b"},{"value":"50","index":"c"},{"value":"75","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"Currently in the entire world, the percent of the population living in urban places is approximately:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"10","index":"a"},{"value":"20","index":"b"},{"value":"50","index":"c"},{"value":"75","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"An important difference between cities and rural places that encourages the growth of cities is that:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"cities are economically more efficient.","index":"a"},{"value":"cities have more educated people.","index":"b"},{"value":"manufacturing requires a city environment.","index":"c"},{"value":"cities are always healthier than rural places.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The most highly urbanized region in the world is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"North America.","index":"a"},{"value":"Europe.","index":"b"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"By 2025 the only region of the world that is expected to still have a larger rural than urban population is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Latin America.","index":"a"},{"value":"Oceania.","index":"b"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"c"},{"value":"Africa.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"If we expect the second most populous city in a country to be half as populous as the largest city, we are referring to the:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"world system theory.","index":"a"},{"value":"rank-size rule.","index":"b"},{"value":"core-periphery model.","index":"c"},{"value":"demographic balancing equation.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The important point to take away from the discussion of Tzintzuntzan, Mexico, is that:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"even in Mexico, small rural places are absorbed by larger urban metropolises.","index":"a"},{"value":"migrants from Mexico to the United States create a situation of population decline in rural Mexico.","index":"b"},{"value":"A small village of artisans with a long indigenous history should not be thought of as rural.","index":"c"},{"value":"Population growth in rural villages leads to migration of younger people to urban places .","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"An important point to take away from the discussion of the urban transition in China is that:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"governments can retard the urban transition, but cannot stop it.","index":"a"},{"value":"the one-child policy has helped to slow down the urban transition.","index":"b"},{"value":"the urban transition is consistent with a Marxian population perspective.","index":"c"},{"value":"China’s largest cities have absorbed most of the growth in the country’s urban population.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"Which of the following statements about urban fertility is true?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Fertility used to be higher than in rural places, but now it is lower.","index":"a"},{"value":"Urban fertility levels in Africa are lower than rural fertility levels in North America.","index":"b"},{"value":"Urban fertility in a country is always at least half the level of rural places.","index":"c"},{"value":"Urban fertility in a country is always lower than rural fertility.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The United Nations defines a city population and its adjacent suburbs as _________ if the total population is at least 750,000:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"a megalopolis","index":"a"},{"value":"a metropolitan statistical area","index":"b"},{"value":"an urban agglomeration","index":"c"},{"value":"a core-based statistical area","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"According to United Nations definitions, a “mega-city” is a city whose population is at least ___ million.","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"5","index":"a"},{"value":"10","index":"b"},{"value":"15","index":"c"},{"value":"20","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The consistently largest mega-city in the world for the past half century has been:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"New York City.","index":"a"},{"value":"London.","index":"b"},{"value":"Tokyo.","index":"c"},{"value":"Mexico City.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The demographic lesson learned from the rats of NIMH is that:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"high density can lead to dysfunctional demographic behavior.","index":"a"},{"value":"rat behavior is significantly different from that of humans.","index":"b"},{"value":"as the population increases in a fixed space, the fertility rate begins to rise.","index":"c"},{"value":"increased density lowers the ability to establish meaningful relationships.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"In which region of the world do nearly three out of four urban residents live in slums?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Southern Asia","index":"a"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa","index":"b"},{"value":"Eastern Asia","index":"c"},{"value":"Northern Africa","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The most rapidly growing parts of American metropolitan areas are currently:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"central cities.","index":"a"},{"value":"suburbs.","index":"b"},{"value":"exurbs.","index":"c"},{"value":"edge cities.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The region of the world with the highest percentage of the urban population living in slums is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Southern Asia.","index":"a"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"b"},{"value":"Northern Africa.","index":"c"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The most highly urban region within the United States is the:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Northeast.","index":"a"},{"value":"Southeast.","index":"b"},{"value":"Midwest.","index":"c"},{"value":"West.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"The concept of an “American apartheid” has been applied to:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the built environment of older Rust Belt cities.","index":"a"},{"value":"residential segregation of blacks in America.","index":"b"},{"value":"ethnic enclaves in large American cities.","index":"c"},{"value":"peri-urban areas being altered by gentrification.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":9},{"question":"To be urban is especially to be spatially concentrated and nonagricultural.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"Ancient cities would have depopulated without migrants because birth rates were higher than death rates.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"The Industrial Revolution occurred in Europe largely because it was already predominantly urban.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"The core-periphery model and world systems theory are both part of the same perspective on urban systems.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"The most important characteristic of a world city is its population size.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"Urban trends show that sprawl is increasingly being replaced by gentrification.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"The urbanization of American blacks occurred at the same time that the process of suburbanization of the white population was taking off.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"In the United States, residential segregation is higher for blacks than for any other racial/ethnic group.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"Because so many immigrants to the United States are from Mexico, the immigrant population in rural areas of the United States is increasing at the expense of urban areas.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"Cities are inherently unsustainable environments on their own.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":9},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT one of the main ways in which demographic changes promote a diversity of family types that are core ingredients of the family and household transition?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Divorce rates have increased","index":"a"},{"value":"People are living longer","index":"b"},{"value":"Fertility is declining","index":"c"},{"value":"The population is increasingly urban","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The nature of a family is that it is a(n) _______ unit whereas a household is a(n) ________unit.","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Consumption; kinship","index":"a"},{"value":"Kinship; residential","index":"b"},{"value":"Economic; nonfamily","index":"c"},{"value":"Residential; family","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Which of the following is LEAST likely to affect your life chances?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Geographic location","index":"a"},{"value":"Individual genetic structure","index":"b"},{"value":"Family social structure","index":"c"},{"value":"Social location","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Which of the following would normally be thought of as part of the set of life chances?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Life expectancy","index":"a"},{"value":"Children ever born","index":"b"},{"value":"Migration experience","index":"c"},{"value":"Educational attainment","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The idea that families are sources of “matching and hatching” in society is captured by the concepts of:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"fusion and fission","index":"a"},{"value":"marriage and divorce","index":"b"},{"value":"birth and death","index":"c"},{"value":"implosion and explosion","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The rise in the number of female-headed households is most apt to be the result of which of the following?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Decline in fertility","index":"a"},{"value":"Decline in mortality","index":"b"},{"value":"Increase in the status of women","index":"c"},{"value":"Increase in the urban population","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The demographic conditions that support the “traditional” family are most likely to occur:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"before the demographic transition starts.","index":"a"},{"value":"in the early stages of the demographic transition.","index":"b"},{"value":"in the middle of the demographic transition.","index":"c"},{"value":"late in the demographic transition.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Which of the following is LEAST likely to occur as a result of a delay in marriage among women?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Rise in status","index":"a"},{"value":"Lower fertility rates","index":"b"},{"value":"Lower likelihood of migrating to an urban area","index":"c"},{"value":"Lower probability of being a second wife in polygamous societies","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The rise in cohabitation in richer countries is associated demographically with:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"delayed marriage.","index":"a"},{"value":"improved contraception.","index":"b"},{"value":"rising levels of education.","index":"c"},{"value":"increased availability of housing for single persons.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The demographic feature that is probably the biggest contributor to the rise in divorce rates is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"the rise in life expectancy.","index":"a"},{"value":"the decline in fertility.","index":"b"},{"value":"the increase in cohabitation.","index":"c"},{"value":"the “me” generation.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The single most important contributor to a person’s life chances is:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"being lifted out of poverty.","index":"a"},{"value":"your gene pool.","index":"b"},{"value":"the status of your occupation.","index":"c"},{"value":"your level of education.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Prior to the U.S. invasion of Iraq, about what percentage of young women aged 15-24 were illiterate in that country?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"10","index":"a"},{"value":"20","index":"b"},{"value":"50","index":"c"},{"value":"70","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The region of the world in which young women are most disadvantaged relative to young men in terms of educational attainment is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"South Central Asia","index":"a"},{"value":"Western Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"Sub-Saharan Africa","index":"c"},{"value":"North Africa","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The cohort of women that have made the biggest gains in the labor force in the United States has been the:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"depression baby cohort","index":"a"},{"value":"“Rosie the riveter” cohort","index":"b"},{"value":"Baby boom cohort","index":"c"},{"value":"Baby bust cohort","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Married women in the United States first began to be accepted in the labor force during which of the following periods?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Civil War","index":"a"},{"value":"World I","index":"b"},{"value":"World War II","index":"c"},{"value":"Vietnam War","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Which of the following is the LEAST likely to describe the global labor force situation of women?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Careers, not jobs","index":"a"},{"value":"Glass ceiling","index":"b"},{"value":"Sticky floor","index":"c"},{"value":"Pay gap","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The inequality in the distribution of income in the United States means that the top 20 percent of earners bring in ___ percent of the nation’s total income, compared to ___ percent for the bottom 20 percent:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"20; 10","index":"a"},{"value":"30; 7","index":"b"},{"value":"40; 5","index":"c"},{"value":"50; 3","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"What percentage of the world’s population currently lives at or below the international definition of poverty?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"10","index":"a"},{"value":"20","index":"b"},{"value":"40","index":"c"},{"value":"60","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"In the United States, wealth is concentrated in which age group?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"35-44","index":"a"},{"value":"45-54","index":"b"},{"value":"55-64","index":"c"},{"value":"65+","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"The concept of dealing with racial discrimination and ethnic relations through the “salad bowl” approach describes which social science model?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Assimilation","index":"a"},{"value":"Segmented assimilation","index":"b"},{"value":"Eugenics","index":"c"},{"value":"Multicultural","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":10},{"question":"Family members differ from household members in that the latter always live together, whereas the former may not.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Because it is not a biological attribute, religion is always considered to be an achieved characteristic.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Despite widespread changes, the traditional family of a married couple with children still accounts for a slight majority of households in the United States.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Hispanic households in the US are more likely than any other group to be headed by a female.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Unlike in the United States, cohabitation has always been the norm in France.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"If women can work and have children, then fertility is less likely to drop to very low levels.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Women are more likely to be holding jobs as managers and administrators than are men.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Incomes for African American families have been rising at a faster rate than for white families, yet the income gap has grown in absolute terms.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Wealth is measured as the sum of your assets and what you owe to others.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Catholics have higher fertility levels than Protestants in the United States.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":10},{"question":"Which of the following is a perspective NOT usually associated with the relationship between population and economic development?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Boomster","index":"a"},{"value":"Cornucopian","index":"b"},{"value":"Doomster","index":"c"},{"value":"Neo-classical","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Economic development refers to:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"An increasing economic output","index":"a"},{"value":"Development of land for industrial purposes","index":"b"},{"value":"Growth in average income","index":"c"},{"value":"All of the above","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"The concept of purchasing power parity is captured by the:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Big Mac Index (BMI)","index":"a"},{"value":"Gross national income","index":"b"},{"value":"Gross national product","index":"c"},{"value":"Per capita income","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following countries has the second largest economy in the world?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"China","index":"a"},{"value":"India","index":"b"},{"value":"Japan","index":"c"},{"value":"United States","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following countries has the highest per person income among this group of four countries?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"China","index":"a"},{"value":"India","index":"b"},{"value":"Mexico","index":"c"},{"value":"Yemen","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Ester Boserup is famous for her idea that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Population growth is an impediment to economic development","index":"a"},{"value":"Population growth can trigger economic development","index":"b"},{"value":"Population growth is not related to economic development","index":"c"},{"value":"Population growth promotes degradation of the environment","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"The idea that human population is the “ultimate resource” is most closely associated with:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Ester Boserup","index":"a"},{"value":"Paul Ehrlich","index":"b"},{"value":"Karl Marx","index":"c"},{"value":"Julian Simon","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following is LEAST likely to promote economic development?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Reducing demographic overhead","index":"a"},{"value":"Increasing the official poverty level","index":"b"},{"value":"Reducing “organizational inefficiencies”","index":"c"},{"value":"Increasing the percentage of women in the paid labor force","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"The United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization estimates that there are currently about ____ people in the world with less than an adequate amount of food.","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"10 million","index":"a"},{"value":"200 million","index":"b"},{"value":"750 million","index":"c"},{"value":"1 billion","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Intensification of agriculture involves:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Putting more acres under production","index":"a"},{"value":"Planting more crops in rain-fed areas of the world","index":"b"},{"value":"Increased yield per acre","index":"c"},{"value":"Putting more people to work on the land","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following is typically NOT part of the Green Revolution:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Improved food distribution system","index":"a"},{"value":"Increased use of irrigation","index":"b"},{"value":"Increased use of fertilizer","index":"c"},{"value":"Increased use of genetically modified seeds","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Current estimates suggest that the maximum number of people who could be fed at the current American diet on a sustainable basis is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Less than 7 billion","index":"a"},{"value":"8-11 billion","index":"b"},{"value":"20-25 billion","index":"c"},{"value":"there is no limit","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following may be the most limiting with respect to sustainable food production for a growing population?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Availability of fertilizers","index":"a"},{"value":"Availability of fresh water","index":"b"},{"value":"Availability of arable land","index":"c"},{"value":"Availability of genetically modified foods","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following countries generates the greatest amount of carbon dioxide emissions in the process of creating goods sold in the United States?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Mexico","index":"a"},{"value":"China","index":"b"},{"value":"India","index":"c"},{"value":"Germany","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following countries is the second biggest contributor of carbon dioxide emissions in the world?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"China","index":"a"},{"value":"India","index":"b"},{"value":"Russia","index":"c"},{"value":"United States","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"If the ecological footprint calculations for the world are correct, then the conclusion would be:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"We have achieved a level of sustainability with respect to resources and population","index":"a"},{"value":"We have about a half century before we will have exceeded our global carrying capacity","index":"b"},{"value":"We are on the verge of exceeding our global carrying capacity","index":"c"},{"value":"We are already in a situation of overshoot","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT an ingredient in Ehrlich’s Impact equation?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Technology","index":"a"},{"value":"Culture","index":"b"},{"value":"Affluence","index":"c"},{"value":"Population","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following was not fully addressed in the Brundtland Commission’s report on sustainable development?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"Alleviation of poverty","index":"a"},{"value":"Population growth","index":"b"},{"value":"Environmental degradation","index":"c"},{"value":"Economic growth","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"Which of the following represents the study that concluded that the optimum population for the world may have been achieved in the 1970s?","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"The ecological footprint study","index":"a"},{"value":"The limits to growth study","index":"b"},{"value":"The tragedy of the commons analysis","index":"c"},{"value":"The global overshoot analysis","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"History suggests that which of the following is the more common demographic response to resource over-utilization at the local level?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"An increase in fertility","index":"a"},{"value":"An drop in fertility","index":"b"},{"value":"Out-migration","index":"c"},{"value":"In-migration","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":11},{"question":"The wealth of a nation can be described as the sum of its natural and human resources.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"The statistical relationship between population growth and per person income at the national level is actually quite weak.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"The historical evidence shows clearly that population growth is inevitably an impediment to economic development.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"Population growth clearly increases the probability of producing the genius who will solve the world’s problems.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"One way to view the Agricultural Revolution is to think of it as a response to the “resource crisis” created by hunter-gatherer populations outstripping the available food supply.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"Increasing the yield per acre comes about through an intensification of agriculture.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"On a per-person basis, the inputs to agriculture peaked in the 1990s and have declined since then.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"The single most important aspect of the Green Revolution is improved irrigation.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"Because of its natural resources, Canada has a higher ecological footprint than the U.S.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"The available evidence suggests that sustainable development is possible if we eliminate poverty from the world.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":11},{"question":"The world population conferences in Rome in 1954 and Belgrade in 1965 differed from subsequent population conferences in that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"they were not hosted by the United Nations.","index":"a"},{"value":"the delegates were academicians, not policy-makers.","index":"b"},{"value":"all subsequent meetings were held outside of Europe.","index":"c"},{"value":"there was no attempt to seriously consider population policy issues.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The main outcome of the 1974 World Population Conference was:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"a statement on global climate change and its demographic impact.","index":"a"},{"value":"a plan for creating a path to sustainable development.","index":"b"},{"value":"a Plan of Action.","index":"c"},{"value":"a statement proposing a global system of family planning.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"An important serendipitous outcome of the 1984 Mexico City Conference was the Global Gag Rule, which reflected Ronald Reagan’s opposition to:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"family planning assistance.","index":"a"},{"value":"population policy.","index":"b"},{"value":"soviet aggression.","index":"c"},{"value":"abortion.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The major outcome of the 1994 Cairo Conference on Population and Development was a consensus that special emphasis should be placed on:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"women’s empowerment.","index":"a"},{"value":"demographic targets.","index":"b"},{"value":"providing global access to safe abortion.","index":"c"},{"value":"reducing the risk of HIV/AIDS.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Which of the following policies to limit fertility would respond most closely to Coale’s first precondition relating to the acceptance of rational choice?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Legalize abortion","index":"a"},{"value":"Higher taxes for each additional child","index":"b"},{"value":"Increase legal age at marriage for women","index":"c"},{"value":"Lower infant and child mortality rates","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Comparing the major outcomes of the 1974 through 1994 conferences with demographic theory, we can see that:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"there is little relationship between the conference outcomes and theory.","index":"a"},{"value":"the conferences endorsed Coale’s three preconditions for a fertility decline, but in reverse order.","index":"b"},{"value":"each conference placed a correct emphasis on how to reduce fertility in developing countries.","index":"c"},{"value":"the conference outcomes almost exactly followed Coales’ three preconditions for a fertility decline.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Governments that think their country’s rate of growth is too high are most apt to be located in:","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"North America.","index":"a"},{"value":"Europe.","index":"b"},{"value":"South America.","index":"c"},{"value":"Africa.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Although the U.S. government does not have an official population policy, it does provide the following:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"USAID support for family planning programs in developing countries.","index":"a"},{"value":"abortion counseling in all states","index":"b"},{"value":"guidance to other countries in how to develop a population policy","index":"c"},{"value":"support for the Equal Rights Amendment","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The country that is projected to add the greatest number of people to the planet between now and the middle of this century is:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"China.","index":"a"},{"value":"India.","index":"b"},{"value":"Mexico.","index":"c"},{"value":"United States.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The region of the world that is expected to experience the highest rate of population growth between now and the middle of this century is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Africa.","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"b"},{"value":"North America.","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The region of the world that is expected to have the highest level of infant mortality in the middle of this century is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Africa.","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"b"},{"value":"North America.","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The region of the world that is expected to have the highest level of fertility in the middle of this century is:","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"Africa.","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"b"},{"value":"North America.","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Family planning programs tend to focus especially on:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"providing condoms.","index":"a"},{"value":"responding to unmet needs for contraception.","index":"b"},{"value":"providing safe abortions.","index":"c"},{"value":"lowering the risk of sexually transmitted disease.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Which of these countries was the first to develop a policy to limit fertility?","answer":"d","option":[{"value":"Mexico","index":"a"},{"value":"China","index":"b"},{"value":"United States","index":"c"},{"value":"India","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"Which of the following policy initiatives would likely do the LEAST to raise fertility levels in Europe?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Increase government-subsidized child care for working mothers","index":"a"},{"value":"Increase legal immigration","index":"b"},{"value":"Increase retirement pensions for working women","index":"c"},{"value":"Increase domestic gender equity","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The region of the world that is expected to have the highest level of net migration in the middle of this century is:","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Africa.","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia.","index":"b"},{"value":"North America.","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"By the year 2050, which of the following regions of the world is least likely to be worried about an aging population?","answer":"a","option":[{"value":"North America","index":"a"},{"value":"East Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"Western Europe","index":"c"},{"value":"Eastern Europe","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The age transition in a country is largely determined by:","answer":"b","option":[{"value":"the increase in life expectancy.","index":"a"},{"value":"the speed of the fertility decline.","index":"b"},{"value":"the status of women.","index":"c"},{"value":"the level of immigration.","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"By the year 2050, which of the following regions of the world will have the lowest percentages of people living in urban areas?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"Africa","index":"a"},{"value":"Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"North America","index":"c"},{"value":"Latin America","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"By the year 2050, which of the following regions of the world is likely to have the oldest age at marriage among women?","answer":"c","option":[{"value":"North America","index":"a"},{"value":"East Asia","index":"b"},{"value":"Western Europe","index":"c"},{"value":"Eastern Europe","index":"d"}],"type":1,"chapter":12},{"question":"The end of World War II brought considerable focus on the demographic issues that the world would face after the war.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The World Population Conference in 1974 in Bucharest was unique in that it was the first to bring together policy makers rather than professional demographers.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The U.S. approach that “development is the best contraceptive” was put forward at the 1984 International Population Conference in Mexico City.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The “Global Gag Rule” refers to the use of condoms.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"China’s one-child policy was never even mentioned at the 1994 International Conference on Population and Development.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The 2004 Population Conference at The Hague set out a new agenda for world population policy.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The most important aspects of the ICPD programme to influence fertility relate to the setting of quotas or targets for specific countries to meet.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The enforced sterilization program in India has been nearly as successful as China’s One-Child Policy in lowering the birth rate.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"France provides an example showing that pronatalist policies can help to produce higher-than-expected fertility levels.","answer":"true","type":0,"chapter":12},{"question":"The US invasion of Iraq in 2003 led to a huge flood of refugees into the United States.","answer":"false","type":0,"chapter":12}]